Inventory of the Klaus Kirchner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Soviet Central Series, 1941-1945; 1-5 (Box 1-5:)
  - Auslands-Nachrichten, 1942 January (Folder 1: 652)
    13x2l cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 60... Mighty front of the people against Hitler-Germany... Eden on his journey to Moscow. Everywhere I had been in Moscow I saw confidence and determination... Attempt to kill the German commander of Paris...]. Photograph: An English Hurricane fighter aircraft on a Russian airfield.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 46, 1942 January (Folder 1: 654)
    13x18 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 46... The families of soldiers have no clothing...]. Photograph: [Frozen, dirty, worn down, that is what these German soldiers look like!...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 47, 1942 January (Folder 1: 655)
    12x18 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 47... Need and hunger are rampant in Germany...]. Photograph: [They did the right thing: laid down their weapons and surrendered to the Red Army.]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 65, 1942 January (Folder 1: 665)
    16x26 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 65... Critical situation of the German Army... The Germans are dying on the Russian snow fields...]. Photograph, see illustration: [English tanks at the Russian front. This is the way the Allies are helping the Soviet Union in the common fight against Hitler.]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 66, 1942 January (Folder 1: 666)
    19x25 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 66... Hitler officers are killing their wounded and frozen soldiers...]. Drawing: [This is how the new year 1942 is beginning - for the Red Army - for the German Army...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 63, 1942 January (Folder 1: 669)
    19x26 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 63 ... The biggest industrial nation in the world, the United States of America, is at war against Germany...]. Photograph: [American aircraft at the Russian front.]
  - Kriegsgefangenschaft ist keine Schande, sondern..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 671)
    13x16 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [Captivity is no shame but the only right way... This way or that way. They trusted Hitler...]. Two photographs: [Dead German soldiers... German prisoners of war in the reading room of a Russian camp.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 49, 1942 January (Folder 1: 672)
    16x24 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 49... No space for the sick from the Eastern Front... Nazis are threatening hungry families of soldiers...]. Photograph of a dead German soldier: [This German soldier will be expected in vain by his relatives at home.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 64, 1942 January (Folder 1: 673)
    18x26 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 64...The United States will produce in 1942: 60,000 airplanes, 45,000 tanks, 20,000 anti-aircraft guns...]. Photomontage: many dead German soldiers: [The retreating Germans leave behind dead and wounded soldiers and war material.]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 68, 1942 January (Folder 1: 674)
    17x26 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 68...Massive losses of the German Luftwaffe near Moscow... Crisis in the German High Command...]. Photograph: [German prisoners of war producing a camp newspaper.]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 69, 1942 January (Folder 1: 679)
    17x25 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 69. Superiority of Soviet Air Force... The Nazis kill sick German soldiers... The reserves of Germany dwindle]. Photograph: [Some German prisoners of war...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 66, 1942 January (Folder 1: 681)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 66... German generals against Hitler... Mass desertions from German garrisons in Poland...]. Photograph: [One of the unharmed armored reconnaissance cars left by the Germans on their hasty retreat.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 51, 1942 January (Folder 1: 682)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1 - 1.1942 - description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 51... German generals against Hitler... Nazis kill sick civilians and soldiers...]. Photograph: [Reading room in a prisoners of war camp. Here at last German prisoners of war have the possibility to read literature Hitler's censorship had prohibited...]
  - Folge ihrem Beispiel! Diese Soldaten haben ihr Leben gerettet…, 1942 January (Folder 1: 683)
    14x17 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1 - 1.1942 - description: [Follow their example! These soldiers saved their lives - they have surrendered to the Red Army. They are out of danger...]
  - Wähle! Wenn Du weiterkämpfst, bist Du verloren! Gibst Du Dich gefangen..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 684)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Choose! If you continue to fight you are lost! If you surrender you will stay alive!...]. Photograph and photomontage.
  - Hier ist der Platz für Dich..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 686)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [This is the spot for you! You will be the next one! German soldiers! Your days are numbered. Today or tomorrow you will be dead also. Why should you die? Keep alive, come on over to us!. ..] Photomontage.
  - Zurück nach Deutschland wollen wir ziehen, in Russland wird uns..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 687)
    17x12 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Back to Germany we want to go, in Russia we will find nothing worthwhile.]. Drawing: German soldiers in a snow storm.
  - Kameraden, auf! Wir ziehen nach Haus! Hier ist's mit Hitlers..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 688)
    17x12 cm - paper: green - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Comrades, Let's go! We want to go home! There will be no victory of Hitler]. Drawing: two German soldiers in a cemetery.
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 71, 1942 January (Folder 1: 689)
    18x24 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 71... Hitler's officers are shooting German soldiers...]. Photograph: German prisoners of war in a Russian camp. [A clean bed covered with white linen - what a pleasure after all the dirt and lice on the front line.]
  - Rüstungsprogramm der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 694)
    15x22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Armament program of the United States of America... Hitler started the war against Soviet Russia without having defeated England. Now, when German troops have to accept one defeat after the other on the snow fields in Russia, Hitler, like a gambler, declared war on America... Do not die for Hitler but live for a free and prosperous Germany]
  - DIE WAHRHEIT ÜBER SOWJETRUSSLAND Nr. 1..., 1942 February (Folder 1: 695)
    16x22 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1. Description: [The truth about Soviet Russia No.1 February 1942. The Soviet war industry is out of reach of the German Luftwaffe...]. Photograph: [Hitler is robbing these Soviet children of their happy childhood.]. Remark: A Soviet propagandist told me many years ago the leaflet series "The truth about Soviet Russia" had to be discontinued, because not enough positive news was available that Germans would have believed at that time.
  - SIE HABEN SICH GEFANGENGEGEBEN. Sie haben ihr Leben gerettet..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 696)
    13x20 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [They have surrendered. They saved their lives. They are feeling fine in Russia and in captivity...]. Two photographs.
  - Papi, wir warten auf Dich! Papi, wo bist Du?..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 697)
    12x19 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Daddy, we are waiting for you! Daddy, where are you? German soldier! Hitler has stolen your family. He wants to make your children orphans. If you want to stay alive and embrace your wife and children again, save your life and come on over to us into captivity...]
  - Letzte Nachrichten für die..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 706)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Latest news for German soldiers: The German people are rising to fight against Hitler. Opposition of German generals against Hitler. The reserves of the German Army are depleted...]. Photograph: German prisoners of war.
  - Keine Briefe aus der Heimat..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 707)
    15x22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [No letters from home. German soldiers!... On Hitler's order letters, from your relatives are not being delivered. Why? ..]. Photograph: [Again no mail!]; drawing: [Back, to your home!"]
  - Hitlers Niederlage ist unausbleiblich..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 708)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler's downfall is unavoidable... This is why the defeat of Hitler-Germany is unavoidable...]. Drawing: [We want to go back to Germany...]
  - Hitler hat schuld am Krieg gegen Sowjetrussland..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 709)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler is guilty of inciting the war against the Soviet-Union... It was Hitler and his clique who started the criminal war against Soviet Russia...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 68, 1942 January (Folder 1: 710)
    14x24 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 68... Declaration of the countries occupied by Germany on the punishment of Hitler-Fascists...]. Photomontage: many dead German soldiers: [At home they are waiting for letters from these dead German soldiers...]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 73, 1942 January (Folder 1: 712)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 73 ... Nazis are afraid of the truth... German soldiers are afraid to fight...]. Photograph: [One of the many tanks the Germans had left behind when they retreated hastily.]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 74, 1942 January (Folder 1: 713)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 74... Crisis in German High Command... German soldiers are surrendering...]. Photograph: [On their hasty retreat from Kaluga the Germans left behind complete trains loaded with war material. In the foreground a direct hit on this train is documented.]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 75, 1942 January (Folder 1: 714)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1 - 1.1942 - description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 75 ... The German troops are fleeing in panic...]. Photograph: [German soldiers and officers are surrendering.]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 76, 1942 January (Folder 1: 715)
    15x24 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 76... German generals against Hitler... How German soldiers perish...]. Photograph: [One of the German vehicles Russians destroyed during their advance.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 53, 1942 January (Folder 1: 716)
    14x21 cm - 2 - rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 53 ... German generals against Hitler... Demonstrations against Hitler in Germany...]. Caricature: [Hitler and Goebbels are changing propaganda slogans for their people.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 54, 1942 January (Folder 1: 717)
    15x23 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 54... Hitler is responsible for the defeat of the German Army...]. Photograph: Military cemetery for German soldiers.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 55, 1942 January (Folder 1: 718)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1 - 1.1942 - description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 55... Germany's oil reserves are dwindling...]. Caricature: Hitler as Napoleon [The wind from the East]
  - BESTIMMUNGEN ÜBER KRIEGSGEFANGENE IN DER SOWJETUNION..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 720)
    15x22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Orders on the treatment of prisoners of war in the Soviet-Union...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 70, 1942 January (Folder 1: 721)
    13x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 70... Hitler murdered Generalfieldmarshal von Reichenau... The main enemy is Hitler-Germany]. Photograph: German POW
  - WER UNTERSCHLAGT DIE SOLDATENBRIEFE? Deutscher Soldat!..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 722)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Who is suppressing soldiers mail? ..]. Letters are being held back by German authorities and reasons are given. Photograph: [Again no mail!].
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 56, 1942 January (Folder 1: 723)
    16x24 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 56... Hitler murdered Generalfieldmarshal von Reichenau...]. Photograph: German POW reading "Front-Illustrierte."
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 71, 1942 January (Folder 1: 725)
    15x24 cm - 2 - preservation: 1 - 1.1942 - description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 71... Hitler is beheading the German Army... The English Air Force is bombarding Hamburg]
  - Deutsche Soldaten an der Ostfront! In der Nähe von..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 726)
    15x21 cm - 4 - red - preservation: 1, edge slightly damaged. Description: [German soldiers on the Eastern Front..]. "Black" leaflet supposedly found by Red Army soldiers: Manifest of a [German Soldiers Committee].
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 77, 1942 January (Folder 1: 727)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 77... Hitler is robbing the German Army of its leadership... Fascists don't allow contact by mail between soldiers and relatives... A desperate war...]. Photograph: [The Germans evacuated Kirov so fast, they left usable tanks. Here are some of these tanks.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 57, 1942 January (Folder 1: 728)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 57... Generalfieldmarshal List arrested, von Brauchitsch disappeared... How the German people are being robbed]. Photomontage: [The German soldiers pay for Hitler's mistakes...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 72, 1942 January (Folder 1: 729)
    15x21 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1 - 1.1942 - description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 72... Hitler's repressions against German generals... Hitler has deceived the German people]. Two photographs.
  - Das Spiel ist verloren..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 730)
    15x24 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1 - 1.1942- description: [The play has been lost...]. Hitler is starting the war and his fate will be the same as Napoleon's. [... An instructive story in six episodes]
  - Zurück! Nach Deutschland!..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 731)
    15x11 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description: [Return! To Germany! The half-frozen destroyed German Army is on the retreat at the complete front...]. Drawing: German soldiers are retreating in snow storm
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 79, 1942 January (Folder 1: 732)
    15x24 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 79 ... Guard-troops are frightening Germans... He who will not surrender will perish...]. Drawing: German soldiers retreating in snow storm
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 79, 1942 January (Folder 1: 733)
    As above, reprint of 732, different code.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 73, 1942 January (Folder 1: 734)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 73 ... Hitler murdered Generalfieldmarshal von Reichenau...The people of America united in their fight against Hitler... Unity of English and Russian workers. The delegation of the Russian trade unions have been greeted with enthusiasm by the English workers...]. Photograph: [From all over the vast Soviet country charitable gifts arrive for the fighters at the front. Our picture shows Red Army soldiers in front of newly arrived gifts.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 58, 1942 January (Folder 1: 735)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 58 ... von Papen against Hitler... Typhoid epidemic in Germany... Advice to surrender...]. Photograph: Two German POWs are reading the Soviet leaflet magazine "Front-Illustrierte" [For the first time they are reading the truth about the situation of the Germany Army on the Soviet-German front.]
  - Folge dem Beispiel dieser 10 Kameraden! DEUTSCHE SOLDATEN!, 1942 January (Folder 1: 736)
    13x21 cm - 4 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Follow the example of these ten comrades! German soldiers! Listen to the voice of your comrades. They have realized it makes no sense to continue to fight and die for this unjust and useless war of Hitler... They write from their Russian captivity:...]. Photograph: Ten German soldiers in captivity.
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 81, 1942 January (Folder 1: 745)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 81... Frost and lice are the worst enemies of the German soldier...]. Photograph: German POWs are playing music.
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 82, 1942 January (Folder 1: 746)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 82... The Russians are beating and chasing the Germans...]. Photomontage: German tanks and dead soldiers on the snow.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 59, 1942 January (Folder 1: 747)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 59... Hitler is taking revenge on German generals...]. Photograph: [Goebbels has forbidden the German population to have Christmas trees. Only in Russian captivity the real German Christmas was celebrated.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 60, 1942 January (Folder 1: 748)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 60... The quarrel among Fascist leaders is growing... Despair is rampant in Germany...]. Photograph: German POWs in a Russian barbershop.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 74, 1942 January (Folder 1: 749)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 74... The Russians have toppled the German plans... Hitler lost his last strong point in front of Moscow... German and Italian troops have been beaten in the Cyreneica...] Photograph: German POW
  - Was hat Hitler der Versuch gekostet Moskau..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 750)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [How much did Hitler's attempt to occupy Moscow... 300,000 dead...1,100 airplanes destroyed..]. Drawing: Dead soldiers.
  - Der Betrüger und Lügner Hitler hat die..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 751)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler, the swindler and liar cheated the soldiers and the German people... From 6th December to 15th January the German army lost more than 300,000 dead soldiers and officers...]. Photomontage, see illustration: The friendly face of Hitler is hiding death.
  - Das russische Volk ist nicht zu besiegen! Als Hitler Sowjetrussland überfiel..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 753)
    14x2 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: The Russian people cannot be defeated! The Russian people fight for a just cause, for their home, and for a free life. This is the reason why the Red Army is beating and driving back continuously the German troops. This is the reason why the Red Army is producing heroes as no other Army in the world.
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 82, 1942 January (Folder 1: 754)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 82... Brilliant success of the Red Army offensive... A sad song of German soldiers...]. Poem, text of the song "Tundra-Lied". The author of this song was Erich Weinert, a famous Communist and leaflet writer in Moscow. Code 753 is erroneously printed on this leaflet
  - SONDERMELDUNG Letzte Nachrichten für die deutschen Soldaten..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 755)
    13x20 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Special announcement. Latest news for German soldiers. New big Russian victory...]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 83, 1942 January (Folder 1: 757)
    15x22 cm - 2 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 83 ... Enormous defeat of the German troops... Rich booty of the Red Army...] Photograph: graves of German soldiers, see illustration.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 75, 1942 January (Folder 1: 758)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 75 ... Catastrophic situation of the German Army...]. Photograph: [Christmas holidays in a POW-camp...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 61, 1942 January (Folder 1: 759)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 61... Inflation in Germany... Hunger revolts in Hamburg...]. Photograph: Each German POW can buy what he wants in the camp shop.
  - Die russischen Betriebe sind für die deutsche Luftwaffe unerreichbar…, 1942 January (Folder 1: 760)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [... The Russian factories cannot be reached by the Luftwaffe...]. Photomontage: [New Russian tanks reach the front]
  - Hitler hat die Schlachtvor Moskau..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 764)
    22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler lost the battle for Moscow!... the defeat of Hitler is unavoidable...]. Photomontage: Dead Germans and destroyed tanks and cannon. [They trusted Hitler and paid with their lives, this end awaits everybody who trusts this insane Hitler.]
  - Eine neue Lüge des Hitlerschen Oberkommandos..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 767)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [A new lie of Hitler's headquarters... Radio Berlin transmitted a message showing the mental confusion of the Hitlerites...]. Drawing: ["Reporting: the frontline is straightened..."]
  - Beute der Sowjettruppen..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 768)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Booty of Soviet troops on the central part of the front from 16th to 25th January, 1942...] Photograph: German tanks abandoned by Germans.
  - Millionen Deutsche setzen ihre Hoffnung..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 769)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: green preservation: 1. Description: The Soviet government is reporting its troops are approaching the German border. [Millions of Germans place their hope on the victory of the Red Army. German soldiers! The truth about the advance of the Red Army to the German border cannot be kept secret...]
  - Das Deutsche Hinterland ist unbeständig..., 1942 January (Folder 1: 772)